Guide to the Jeanine Michna-Bales Photographs, 2013-2015 RL.11285
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jeanine Michna-Bales photographs
2013-2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Michna-Bales, Jeanine
RL.11285
7 Linear Feet
Jeanine Michna-Bales is a conceptual documentary photographer based in Dallas, Texas. Her series "Through Darkness to Light: Seeking Freedom on the Underground Railroad" won the 2016 ADA Collection Award for Documentarians of the American South. The project comprises 40 color photographs of a route taken by travelers on the Underground Railroad between 1800 and the end of the Civil War. Michna-Bales researched the route over a decade and photographed the locations between 2012 and 2015.
Arrangement
Arranged by creator.
Biographical / Historical
Jeanine Michna-Bales is a documentary photographer based in Dallas, Texas. Her work has been shown throughout the United States as well as in online publications and blogs.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Jeanine Michna-Bales Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2016.
Collection Overview
The Jeanine Michna-Bales photographs comprise her series "Through Darkness to Light: Seeking Freedom on the Underground Railroad," which won the 2016 ADA Collection Award for Documentarians of the American South. The series contains (39) 17"x24.5" color photographs printed on 21"x28.5" paper and (1) 17"x70.75" panoramic photograph printed on 21"x74.75" paper. Images are digital chromogenic prints printed on Kodak Endura Lustre paper printed in 2016 by Steve Clayton at Holland Photo Imaging in Austin, Texas.
Michna-Bales provided the following abstract of her work:
They left during the middle of the night – oftentimes carrying little more than the knowledge that moss grows on the northern side of trees. An estimated 100,000 slaves between 1800 and the end of the Civil War chose to embark on this journey of untold hardships in search of freedom. Fugitives traveled roughly 20 miles each night traversing rugged terrain while enduring all the hardships that Mother Nature could bring to bear. Occasionally, they were guided from one secret, safe location to the next by an ever-changing, clandestine group known as the Underground Railroad. From a cotton plantation in Louisiana all the way north to Canada, this series of photographs can help us imagine what the long road to freedom may have looked like as seen through the eyes of one of those who made this epic journey.
The documented route took over a decade to piece together. Images were captured digitally over a three-year period starting in the Fall of 2012. The images have been displayed with found text from the time period, such as quotes from various participants, to help give the viewer a better understanding of circumstances surrounding a person’s journey to freedom.
Documentary Photography; Louisiana -- Pictorial works; Mississippi -- Pictorial works; Alabama -- Pictorial works; Tennessee -- Pictorial works; Kentucky -- Pictorial works; Indiana -- Pictorial works; Ontario -- Pictorial works; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Michna-Bales, Jeanine
- Through Darkness to Light: Seeking Freedom on the Underground Railroad, 40 Photographic Prints
  - Decision to Leave, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Magnolia Plantation on the Cane River, Louisiana
  - Southern Pine Forest, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Following El Camino Real; LaSalle Parish, Louisiana
  - Catching a Breath, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    LaSalle Parish, Louisiana
  - Stopover, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Frogmore Plantation; Concordia Parish, Louisiana
  - Sunken Trace, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Claiborne County, Mississippi
  - Determining Truth North in the Rain, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Along the southern part of the Old Natchez Trace, Mississippi
  - Cypress Swamp, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Middle Mississippi
  - Off the Beaten Path, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Along the Yockanookany River, Mississippi
  - Doubling Back, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Webster County, Mississippi
  - Keep Going, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Crossing the Tennessee River; Colbert County, Alabama
  - Twisted Thicket, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Lawrence County, Tennessee
  - Devil's Backbone, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Lewis County, Tennessee
  - Shelter from the Storm, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Hickman County, Tennessee
  - Tennessee Valley Divide, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Williamson County, Tennessee
  - Taking to the Hollow, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Davidson County, Tennessee
  - Hidden in Plain Sight, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Rose Mont Plantation; Sumner County, Tennessee
  - A Lesson in Astronomy, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Southern Kentucky
  - Fleeing the Torches, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Warren County, Kentucky
  - Hidden Passage, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Mammoth Cave; Barren County, Kentucky
  - Following the Green River, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Edmonson County, Kentucky
  - Racing the Stars, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Between Oldham and Shelby Counties, Kentucky
  - over the Hills, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    North Trimble County, Kentucky
  - The River Jordan, 2014; Panoramic image. Image measures 17" by 70.75". (Oversize-image 1)
    First view of a free state, crossing the Ohio River to Indiana
  - Eagle Hollow from Hunter's Bottom, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Just Across the Ohio River, Indiana
  - Follow the Drinking Gourd, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jefferson County, Indiana
  - Nightlight, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Passing into Fayette County, Indiana
  - Friend or Foe?, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Station just outside Metamora, Indiana
  - A Brief Respite, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Abolitionist William Beard’s house, Union County, Indiana
  - Look for the Gray Barn Out Back, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Joshua Eliason Jr. barnyards and farmhouse, with a tunnel leading underneath the road to another station, Centerville, Indiana
  - A Safe Place to Regroup, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    House of Levi Coffin, who was unofficially dubbed the president of the Underground Railroad. Fountain City (formerly Newport), Indiana
  - Approaching the Seminary, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Near Spartanburg, Indiana
  - Taking Cover with the Fireflies, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    North of Winchester, Indiana
  - On the Safest Route, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    James and Rachel Sillivan’s cabin, Pennville (formerly Camden), Indiana
  - Walk Along the Ridge, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Between the Maumee and St. Joseph Rivers. Braun-Leslie House, Fort Wayne, Indiana
  - Dirt Road, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Outside Coldwater, Michigan
  - "Liberty to the Fugitive Captive", 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Waiting for the all-clear to head to the Captain John Lowry Station; Lodi Plains Cemetery, Nutting’s Corner, Michigan
  - The Beacon Tree, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Spring Hill Farm, Macomb County, Michigan
  - Scrub Field, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Leaving Reverend Oren Cook Thompson Station, St. Clair County, Michigan
  - Within Reach, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Crossing the St. Clair River to Canada just south of Port Huron, Michigan
  - Freedom, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Canadian soil; Sarnia, Ontario